<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>blog</title>
    <link href="https://heyally.ai/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://heyally.ai/blog" />
    <updated>2025-12-18T16:41:06-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Brian Gladu</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://heyally.ai/blog</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Themes for Ally!</title>
        <author>
            <name>Brian Gladu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://heyally.ai/blog/themes-for-ally/"/>
        <id>https://heyally.ai/blog/themes-for-ally/</id>
            <category term="updates"/>
            <category term="macos"/>
            <category term="ios"/>

        <updated>2025-12-11T17:12:21-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    Now you can customize the look and feel of Ally on iOS and macOS with three themes. Newspaper theme Newspaper is a grayscale monochrome theme for people who like light themes. It has a near white background, containers and fields are shades of gray, and text is near black gray. Monochrome theme For dark theme lovers, monochrome has a near black background, dark container backgrounds, and near white text. Primary theme My personal favorite, Primary&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                
  <p>
    Now you can customize the look and feel of Ally on iOS and macOS with three themes.<br><br><strong>Newspaper theme<br></strong>Newspaper is a grayscale monochrome theme for people who like light themes. It has a near white background, containers and fields are shades of gray, and text is near black gray.<br>
  </p>

    <figure class="post__image post__image--center">
      <img loading="lazy" src="https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.38.20-PM-1.png" height="1177" width="2071" alt=""  sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.38.20-PM-1-xs.webp 640w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.38.20-PM-1-sm.webp 768w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.38.20-PM-1-md.webp 1024w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.38.20-PM-1-lg.webp 1366w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.38.20-PM-1-xl.webp 1600w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.38.20-PM-1-2xl.webp 1920w">
      
    </figure>

  <p>
    <b>Monochrome theme<br></b>For dark theme lovers, monochrome has a near black background, dark container backgrounds, and near white text.<br>
  </p>

    <figure class="post__image post__image--center">
      <img loading="lazy" src="https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.48.34-PM-1.png" height="1177" width="2780" alt=""  sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.48.34-PM-1-xs.webp 640w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.48.34-PM-1-sm.webp 768w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.48.34-PM-1-md.webp 1024w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.48.34-PM-1-lg.webp 1366w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.48.34-PM-1-xl.webp 1600w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.48.34-PM-1-2xl.webp 1920w">
      
    </figure>

  <p>
    <b>Primary theme<br></b>My personal favorite, Primary is a low contrast theme with a brown background, green highlights, a text is shades of cream-colored off whites. The theme for those who like a bit of color.<br>
  </p>

    <figure class="post__image post__image--center">
      <img loading="lazy" src="https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.29.59-PM-1-2.png" height="1177" width="1134" alt=""  sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.29.59-PM-1-2-xs.webp 640w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.29.59-PM-1-2-sm.webp 768w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.29.59-PM-1-2-md.webp 1024w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.29.59-PM-1-2-lg.webp 1366w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.29.59-PM-1-2-xl.webp 1600w ,https://heyally.ai/blog/media/posts/11/responsive/Screenshot-2025-12-11-at-2.29.59-PM-1-2-2xl.webp 1920w">
      
    </figure>

  <p>
    This is just the beginning... what other themes would you like to see? What fonts would you like Ally to support?&nbsp;
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>iPhone Action button shortcut support for iOS</title>
        <author>
            <name>Brian Gladu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://heyally.ai/blog/ios-action-button/"/>
        <id>https://heyally.ai/blog/ios-action-button/</id>
            <category term="updates"/>
            <category term="ios"/>

        <updated>2025-12-08T17:43:37-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    One of the core goals of Ally as a productivity solution is ensuring communication with Ally is fast and easy. You should be able to add a todo, capture an idea, or get the date of your next meeting without friction. There’s no faster way to capture quick thoughts, reminders, and notes than with dictation and there’s no faster way to start dictation than with the iPhone Action button, a configurable hardware button on 14,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>One of the core goals of Ally as a productivity solution is ensuring communication with Ally is fast and easy. You should be able to add a todo, capture an idea, or get the date of your next meeting without friction.</p><p>There’s no faster way to capture quick thoughts, reminders, and notes than with dictation and there’s no faster way to start dictation than with the <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/use-and-customize-the-action-button-iphe89d61d66/ios">iPhone Action button</a>, a configurable hardware button on 14, 15, 16, and 17 series iPhones.</p><p>The <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/ally-ai-for-life/id6752736179">iOS app</a> was recently updated to include an Action button shortcut that instantly opens <a href="https://heyally.ai">the Ally AI iOS app</a> and starts a recording. </p><p>This means you can capture any thought instantly any time your phone is near with just a single click. It’s the fastest, most frictionless way to pass information from your head to Ally where it can be organized and retrieved when needed.</p><p>It’s a great way to get things out of your head and into your Ally Inbox where you can then store, organize, and leverage it in the future. </p><h2 id="how-to-configure-your-iphones-action-button-to-quickly-capture-and-transcribe-voice-notes">How to configure your iPhone’s Action button to quickly capture and transcribe voice notes:</h2>
<ol>
<li><p>Install the <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/ally-ai-for-life/id6752736179">Ally AI iOS app</a> from the iOS app store. </p></li>
<li><p>Open the Settings app on your iPhone. </p></li>
<li><p>Scroll down to find Action Button in the list and tap it to open its options. </p></li>
<li><p>Swipe right to left to scroll through the options until you reach Shortcut. </p></li>
<li><p>Press the selector and search the available shortcuts for <code>Ally</code>. </p></li>
<li><p>Choose <code>Start Recording</code> by pressing it. </p></li>
<li><p>Close the Settings app. </p></li>
<li><p>Press and hold the Action button on your phone to do a test recording.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Being able to quickly capture voice notes is like a super power. You can get things out of your head and into a productivity system with minimal friction and get back to whatever needs your attention. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Top macOS markdown editors 2026</title>
        <author>
            <name>Brian Gladu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://heyally.ai/blog/mac-markdown-editors-2026/"/>
        <id>https://heyally.ai/blog/mac-markdown-editors-2026/</id>
            <category term="productivity"/>
            <category term="macos"/>

        <updated>2025-12-08T14:44:28-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    Markdown editors are a personal thing. For me, my priorities are: One of the originals, and still one of the best, for anyone looking for a lightweight, document-focused editing experience. It’s refined, elegant, and it does its job well. So, it’s no surprise it’s been the go-to mac app for Markdown editing for over a decade now. iA Writer integrates a simple file management solution that may be adequate for most users, but may not&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Markdown editors are a personal thing. For me, my priorities are:</p><ol>
<li><strong>Fast:</strong> I should be able to launch it and create a new document near instantly.</li>
<li><strong>Beautiful:</strong> Markdown text should render nicely.</li>
<li><strong>Simple:</strong> The tool should get out of your way so you can focus on productivity.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="ia-writer"><a href="https://ia.net/writer">iA Writer</a></h2>
<p>One of the originals, and still one of the best, for anyone looking for a lightweight, document-focused editing experience. It’s refined, elegant, and it does its job well. So, it’s no surprise it’s been the go-to mac app for Markdown editing for over a decade now. </p><p>iA Writer integrates a simple file management solution that may be adequate for most users, but may not be enough for power users trying to create a productivity system or PKM style “second brain.” Those users may be more interested in something like Obsidian… </p><h2 id="obsidian"><a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a></h2>
<p>No list of markdown editors would be complete without the undisputed king of robust markdown editing. If you’re looking for a markdown editing experience that can become a full productivity system, then you’ll find no peer. It has a massive library of community created plugins for pretty much anything. </p><p>Note that Obsidian’s strength is also its curse. Some users find the complexity created by its near limitless configuration options overwhelming. Some find that they end up spending more time maintaining their Obsidian-based productivity system than they do actually being productive.</p><h2 id="typora"><a href="https://typora.io/">Typora</a></h2>
<p>Typora is often compared to iA Writer with good reason. They’re both minimalistic and simple. To highlight the major difference, I’d say that Typora is more focused on advanced editing capabilities while iA Writer seeks to be a more simplified experience to keep you creative and productive. In other words, if you need advanced markdown features like math/diagram support, then Typora may be your best option.  </p><h2 id="bear"><a href="https://bear.app/">Bear</a></h2>
<p>When Bear came onto the scene, it redefined elegance for iOS and macOS productivity apps. Its tag-first approach to organizing notes remains unique and one of the most flexible ways to organize a large library of notes. </p><p>Where some users may want more is around advanced personal knowledge management (PKM) and automation features. In that case, you’re looking to build a sophisticated productivity system, something like Obsidian may be a better fit.</p><p>I have a hard time criticizing it, it’s my favorite macOS app of all time, and a huge inspiration for… </p><h2 id="ally"><a href="https://heyally.ai/">Ally</a></h2>
<p>A new comer, what makes Ally unique is its AI-first approach. There’s no separation between your markdown docs and what the AI sees so you can quickly switch back and forth between editing/creation and an AI that’s always in sync. It also offers a uniquely flexible node system where nodes are simulateously markdown docs, folders, and chats so you can add new nodes without wasting any resources on whether you need a folder, doc, or chat. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Ally macOS app gets native full screen mode support</title>
        <author>
            <name>Brian Gladu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://heyally.ai/blog/macos-full-screen-mode/"/>
        <id>https://heyally.ai/blog/macos-full-screen-mode/</id>
            <category term="updates"/>
            <category term="macos"/>

        <updated>2025-12-07T16:30:12-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    Long periods of unbroken concentration, that most of us require to achieve the deep focus that leads to “deep work,” are increasingly challenging to come by. We know our best work comes from focus, but it can be challenging to tailor our digital workspaces to minimize distractions. Even on macOS, an operating system built for the desktop/laptop format, and so tailored toward productivity, work, and creation, they’re, at least in some ways, intentionally designed to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Long periods of unbroken concentration, that most of us require to achieve the deep focus that leads to “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Deep-Work-Focused-Success-Distracted/dp/1455586692">deep work</a>,” are increasingly challenging to come by.</p><p>We know our best work comes from focus, but it can be challenging to tailor our digital workspaces to minimize distractions. Even on macOS, an operating system built for the desktop/laptop format, and so tailored toward productivity, work, and creation, they’re, at least in some ways, intentionally <em>designed to divert our attention away from whatever we’re trying to do</em>, such as for alerts and notifications. There’s also a row of colorful icons tempting us to stray from our intended focus. </p><p><a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/mac-help/use-apps-in-full-screen-mchl9c21d2be/mac">macOS’s full-screen mode</a> helps with focus and concentration, thereby improving our ability to achieve the flow state many of us need to do our best work. It simply minimizes distracting visual clutter by devoting the entire screen to a single app. This is an app experience that’s default behavior on Windows, but not macOS. Both modes have their uses and benefits, so it doesn’t really make sense to frame it as a “right or wrong” debate. </p><p>But, for deep work, work that requires prolonged intense focus to be productive, many of us benefit from minimal distraction, and things like macOS’s full-screen mode help a lot by massively trimming distracting and potentially overwhelming visual noise. For anyone closer to the challenging end of the attention spectrum, the “multi-task mode” that macOS encourages by default can actually be a sneaky productivity killer. It can feel like we’re getting a lot done, but we’re really shuffling around windows and never really delving deep enough into any particular thing to solve a complex problem, come up with a great new idea, or uncover important nuance in a data set.  </p><p>Now <a href="https://heyally.ai">Ally</a> supports full-screen mode so you can laser focus on whatever doc you’re creating, web clipping you’re reading, or AI chat you’re having. </p><p>To get started, <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/ally-ai-for-life/id6752736179">download the latest version of the Ally AI app from the macOS app store</a>. </p><p>With the <a href="https://heyally.ai">Ally app</a> running, press the key combination <code>fn + f</code> or click the green circle icon in the upper left-hand corner of the app. </p><p>To exit full screen mode, you can press <code>esc</code>, <code>fn + f</code> again, or click the green circle icon that appears when you hover the upper left-hand corner of the app while in full screen mode.</p><p>You can also arrange the Ally app side by side with other apps, such as a web browser or PDF viewer, by clicking and holding the green circle icon, then selecting one of the tile options to arrange the window. </p><p>Now you can focus better with fewer visual distractions competing for your attention. </p><p>I’ll continue looking for new ways to leverage Apple’s ecosystem to make productivity easier with Ally. If you have an idea, <a href="mailto:hi@heyally.ai">let me know</a> or <a href="https://ally.eververse.ai/">submit as a feature request</a> and I’ll add it to the community-driven roadmap. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Tools to connect to many LLMs at once</title>
        <author>
            <name>Brian Gladu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://heyally.ai/blog/tools-to-connect-to-many-llms-at-once/"/>
        <id>https://heyally.ai/blog/tools-to-connect-to-many-llms-at-once/</id>
            <category term="llms"/>
            <category term="ai"/>

        <updated>2025-12-07T14:21:16-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    To access the latest frontier AI models from Anthropic, OpenAI, Google, Perplexity, and Deepseek, you could pay $100 or more in monthly subscriptions. A cost-saving alternative is to use an AI chat interface — sometimes referred to as a “chatbot UI” or “LLM frontend” (there doesn’t appear to be an agreed upon naming convention). These apps allow you to connect to LLMs via their APIs. This way, you pay only for your actual usage. This approach&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>To access the latest frontier AI models from Anthropic, OpenAI, Google, Perplexity, and Deepseek, you could pay $100 or more in monthly subscriptions. </p><p>A cost-saving alternative is to use an AI chat interface — sometimes referred to as a “chatbot UI” or “LLM frontend” (there doesn’t appear to be an agreed upon naming convention). These apps allow you to connect to LLMs via their APIs. This way, you pay only for your actual usage. </p><p>This approach has a few advantages:</p><ol>
<li><p><strong>Multi-model access</strong> - With a frontend UI you can access any model with an OpenAPI compatible API. You could be coding with Claude, then switch to Deepseek to plan your next vacation, then throw an enormous PDF at Gemini for some quick Q&amp;A. </p></li>
<li><p><strong>Cost-savings</strong> - What’s great about accessing LLMs via the API is that, for most people, it is much less expensive because you’re only paying for your actual usage. Unless you’re an extremely heavy user, you’ll probably find that your total API costs — across all models — ends up being less than $10 a month. </p></li>
<li><p><strong>Cool features</strong> - Chatbot UI’s tend to clone features added by the major players and will often explore experimental or highly speclialized new features you won’t find in any of the UIs of the major AI players. You’ll be able to run open source models locally, test multiple models side-by-side, easily add RAG to give your AI specialized knowledge, and more. </p></li>
<li><p><strong>Easier to manage</strong> - It’s much easier to manage prompts, system instructions, stored memories, and RAG databases from one place instead of needing to keep this kind of LLM context data consistent and up-to-date across the various LLM platforms.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>And this approach has downsides:</p><ol>
<li><p><strong>You’ll lose access to some of the specialized, unique features</strong> - The Perplexity UI has some great features like Projects and Pages. OpenAI’s desktop app can connect to apps you’re running locally so it can “see” what you’re doing. Sometimes these features have been re-created by the frontend UIs in this list and sometimes they haven’t. More than once since cancelling my subscription to the big providers, I’ve signed back up for a month or two to test out their latest features. Usually I find that whatever feature it was isn’t as valuable as I’d hoped and I return to using my frontend interface. </p></li>
<li><p><strong>You’ll need to invest time up front</strong> - There’s a little more work involved with getting this set up, but don’t let it intimidate you. You’ll need to sign up for API keys for the models you want to use, which is tedious since you’ll need to input your billing info for each one. If you want to add all the major models you’ll probably be looking at 30 minutes or so. But, you can dip your toe into this without commiting to connecting to 10 different LLM APIs. You can connect just one API, use the app for a bit, and decide whether you want to test a different one or add more more models.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Less polish</strong> - I love the OpenAI UI and haven’t found an alternative chatbot UI that’s as visually pleasing, responsive, and organized. It’s not perfect, but I find myself wishing that one of these apps would just clone it and add folders and workspaces. Also, most of these chatbot UI apps are undergoing active development from small teams so they change quickly, things break, etc. These apps aren’t going through the same extensive product testing and validation processes Google, OpenAI, etc. are using before they release an update. </p></li>
<li><p><strong>Time spent tinkering</strong> - This is really an add on to item 3. Due to “lack of polish,” these apps tend to be more buggy and have more issues than you’re probably used to. Depending on whether you’re interested in learning new tech skills, you’ll find the time you spend setting this up and using it day to day to be a minor annoyance that doubles as a learning opportunity, or an intolerable inconvenience and waste of precious time. If you simply “need things to work” more than you’re interested in learning — about LLMs and tech in general — this may not be the right path for you.</p></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="about-this-list-of-llm-interfaces">About this list of LLM interfaces</h2>
<p>Before we jump into the list, let’s talk a bit about methodology, perspective, and biases. I’ve tried to pull out the pros and cons that seem important to someone looking for an LLM interface but, for instance, I’m not a coder, so I don’t have insight into which UI is best for software development and I don’t bother to review Cursor and other UIs specializing in code generation. </p><p>I take into account: </p><ul>
<li><strong>Cost / licensing</strong> - Most of the apps are free but I point out where some features are gated behind a paid plan. </li>
<li><strong>Tech savviness required</strong> - For instance, do you need to use or understand code?</li>
<li><strong>Installation process</strong> - Does it offer Docker installation or will you be installing dependencies via command line?</li>
<li><strong>Web-based or native app?</strong> Can it be run locally? Can it be self-hosted and accessed online? </li>
<li><strong>Ability to run local and API models?</strong> Does it integrate with ollama or similar?</li>
<li><strong>Mobile experience</strong> - Is it well-optimized for small screens?</li>
<li><strong>Audio experience</strong> - How does the TTS and STT experience measure up? I use OpenAI’s advanced speech mode as my comparison. </li>
<li><strong>My overall rating</strong> - This is where I attempt to rate each of these apps based on my overall experience with it. It’s not an average of all the other scores, or a ranking by the total of the scores, or anything like that. It’s just my opinion.</li>
</ul>
<p>I have no personal connection to the developers of these apps and I am not using any affiliate links or benefiting financially in any way. </p><p>If you have an app you’d like to see listed here, I’d love to try it, email me at: <a href="mailto:&#x62;&#x72;&#105;&#x61;&#110;&#x67;&#x6c;&#x61;&#100;&#x75;&#x40;&#x67;&#109;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#46;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;">&#x62;&#x72;&#105;&#x61;&#110;&#x67;&#x6c;&#x61;&#100;&#x75;&#x40;&#x67;&#109;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#46;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;</a>. If you’re the developer of one of these apps and you’d like to discuss something I’ve said here, I’d love to chat! Don’t hesitate to email me. </p><h1 id="browser-based-solutions">Browser-based solutions</h1>
<p>These apps can be exposed to the web or they can be locally accessed (via a browser). They often install via Docker. If you aren’t already using Docker apps, I highly recommend you dip your toe into it! It opens up a world of open source software and it really isn’t as technically challenging as it may appear. In fact, the whole point of it is to make setting up and using apps easier. That’s a topic for a different post though. </p><h2 id="openwebui"><a href="https://github.com/open-webui/open-webui">openwebui</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://github.com/open-webui/open-webui">Github stars: 70k</a>  |  <a href="https://docs.openwebui.com/roadmap/">Roadmap</a></p><blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: Openwebui’s standout feature is its community of user-created functions (that are used to add custom functionality). It’s popular because it’s one of the best chatbot UI’s available at the moment. </p></blockquote>
<p>One of the better-known AI interfaces, openwebui is also one of the most powerful and full-featured. It’s extensive feature set includes memory management, support for TTS and STT (audio), workspaces (which allow you to specify custom instructions), tags and folders for conversation management, and more. </p><p>It’s a web app that can be run locally (you’ll still access it via a browser window). It can be set up via Docker, which can make the installation process much faster and less error-prone for the less technical. </p><p>OpenwebUI’s major, standout strength is its community and extensibility. A <a href="https://openwebui.com/">web-based community portal</a> offers a collection of community-developed custom functions that add functionality and capabilities. It also offers a companion app, <a href="https://github.com/open-webui/pipelines">Pipelines</a>, for adding major functionality like supporting new model providers. I imagine for a developer, the openness and extensibility of openwebui is a lot of fun. For me, a non-developer, it can sometimes be challenging. Functions or Pipelines I install from the community don’t always work or are buggy. This can give the app an unpolished or unstable feel that I find unpleasant since I use AI constantly throughout the day at work and at home. If you need it to “just work” you might find a vanilla installation works great but some of the community functions cause issues. </p><p>The UI itself is good, but not great. The mobile UI especially could use some optimization. Folders were added recently which is a huge step up from the tags-only organization system it had before. Visually, the folder icons are quite small which is an odd design choice I’m seeing more and more. Also, in other apps you’re able to add custom instructions onto folders, but openwebui does not currently offer that. </p><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody><tr>
<td>Price</td>
<td>Free</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Open source?</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Technical skills required</td>
<td>Docker</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Installation</td>
<td>Docker</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Browser-based or native?</td>
<td>Browser</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Run local models?</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mobile experience</td>
<td>3/5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Audio experience</td>
<td>3/5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Overall rating</td>
<td>4/5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<h3 id="standout-features">Standout features:</h3>
<ul>
<li>A large community of many user-created custom functions (plugins) is openwebui’s “killer feature” you won’t find anywhere else. </li>
<li>Create multiple workspaces for separation and shared context between conversations</li>
<li>Speech support. Many frontend UI’s for AI don’t offer this. It’s not up to OpenAI’s Advanced Voice mode, yet. There’s a signficant delay between what you say and the LLM’s response. Also, no interruption (or even listening) while the LLMs response is being read.</li>
<li>Memory support that works similarly to OpenAI’s though out of the box you’ll need to click an “add to memory” button. There are also “autolearning” functions available via the community but I haven’t gotten these to work reliably yet.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="weaknesses">Weaknesses:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Conversation organization</li>
<li>Speech mode is far behind what the frontier models are offering</li>
<li>Community functions aren’t well-curated - can be buggy and unreliable</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="chatbotui">chatbotui</h2>
<p><a href="https://github.com/mckaywrigley/chatbot-ui">29.6k github stars</a> | Not maintained</p><p>This entry will be short and it pains me that it is. What began as one of the most promising interfaces seems to have become an abandoned project. It’s still second only to the OpenAI UI in my mind. You can still set it up and use it, it just hasn’t kept pace with the rapid developments in the space. If you just want to have conversations with a chatbot and organize your threads into folders, this might be a great app for you. Just be aware that no one is patching security holes or adding new features at this time. One of the unfortunate downsides to the open source software scene is that isn’t uncommon. </p><p>If you find an app you like, look for an opportunity to donate to the developers. It really, really does make a difference. </p><h1 id="options-that-run-locally">Options that run locally</h1>
<p>These apps don’t require Docker or touching a command line tool so they’re a great option for anyone who just wants to get up and running with an API frontend without learning something new. </p><p>I do encourage you to learn Docker and get experience using command line tools. Neither is as intimidating or difficult as they may seem. You’ll need patience more than technical skills or intelligence. </p><h2 id="msty"><a href="https://msty.app/">msty</a></h2>
<p>Not on github &amp; not open source
Free, with some perk-like features accessible with a one-time payment</p><p>I find myself using both Msty and OpenWebUI a lot. They offer similar features and they’re both powerful — you can tweak as many model parameters as you like. They both make it really easy to use a combinaton of local models (via ollama) and proprietary models (via APIs). It’s really cool comparing the output from some of the smaller open source models to the output of the bleeding edge models. </p><p>Msty stands out in my mind as having a better folder and conversation organization system than openwebui (you can add custom instructions onto folders so that all conversations created in that folder are given context for that topic/project), it has better model comparison tools (you can send the same prompt to 2 or more models at once, split off conversations, and more. </p><p>While I’m comparing it to openwebui, I should point out one of openwebui’s strengths – its openness. There’s a large community of openwebui who contribute functions which are basically customizations or enhancements or even new features. It can be hit or miss on how buggy they are, but overall it’s a nice, signficant advantage openwebui has over msty, as a closed source product, will likely never have. </p><p>There are also some cool features you won’t see anywhere else like the ability to dig deeper into key words. It’s free, but there is a paid option that gives you early access to new features and unlocks some bells and whistles. Some companies aggressively gate their best features behind paid plans but Msty gives you even its most powerful features free. You’d get the paid plan mostly to support its development vs upgrading because you need access to this or that feature to get your work done. I really like that approach. </p><p>I do wish Msty was snappier. For an app running natively and locally, I expect it to be extremely responsive but it isn’t, at times. For instance, when switching between workplaces. Even smaller operations like switching between conversations feels just a titch laggy. </p><p>Another criticism would be that I think the UI could use some work. I’m not sure if it’s a new design trend or what, but a lot of LLM frontend apps use very small icons for the folders. This is unintuitive to me because in my mind folders should be bigger (since, they’re collections of all the files within them). It just goes against what I expect for folders to be visually smaller than files. It’s a small thing, but it bugs me. Another small nuisance that plagues me is that, even though it can be customized and tweaked in some ways, I can’t get the typography to feel quite right. There are other UI elements that could use some tweaking and polish in my mind. None of them is a dealbreaker and it’s unfair of me to mention so many slight imperfections for Msty and gloss over some much more significant ones in other apps. Just take into account that I use it a lot so it’s imperfections bug me more often and are more top of mind. </p><p>It’s a great app and the fact that I use it more than any other says a lot and reveals my opinion better than my focus on its minor flaws. </p><h2 id="jan"><a href="https://jan.ai/">jan</a></h2>
<p>Jan is an interesting app because if you fit its use case it’s perfect, but more advanced users will find it unuseable. </p><p>It’s available for Mac, Windows, and Linux. It makes running local models really easy. There’s a tab where you can quickly browse and download new models. It even warns you if a model is likely to struggle running on your system. In settings, you’re able to add API keys for a solid list of hosted providers. If that’s all you’re looking for, this is probably a really solid choice. </p><p>However, if you’re looking for pretty much any power feature — like folders, memory management, side-by-side conversations, or even access to advanced model parameter settings — this probably isn’t the app for you. </p><p>It feels snappy and polished. It looks like new features are well-planned and well-execuated. It’s one of those apps that feels like it was created by a thoughtful, passionate developer. </p><p>But without more advanced features and functionality, I think it will rarely be at the top of anyone’s list. The features it lacks are kind of essential for anyone who is using LLMs professionally, interested in prompt engineering, etc. </p><h2 id="lm-studio">LM studio</h2>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
